The stock market was not happy with
HSBC. What should have been a small
little nothing, a $400 million loan loss
to an Irish entity with a name that
sounds like a Star Wars droid,
AGFWHCO185,
it ended up pulling the curtain back a
little bit further on the private credit
mess, exposing more big cracks in that
foundation. As did the comments from
Apollo CEO, where he used the words
contagion
and egregious.
And the egregious part of it was about
insurance companies, because it's
insurance companies, not necessarily big
banks, that were at the center of this
still growing mess. And we can't take
the big banks out of it because they are
major suppliers of funding for the whole
onion. And it really is an onion with
many different layers to it. And we're
going to peel back a couple of them here
with huge, if inadvertent, assistance
from HSBC, as well as Marc Rowan of
Apollo. Now, Mr. Rowan would know an
onion when he sees one, because Apollo
is deep in the insurance business. And
in his pretty shocking comments from
earlier today, the Wall Street exec
first admitted that insurance firms, the
ones that he oversees, get this, they're
pulling back on risky credit. Remember,
as I always say, it's not what they say,
it's what they do. Because they always
say there's nothing to worry about. And
what Apollo's insurance companies are
doing is indeed huge news.
As is the other part of his statement,
which fits together with what we're
going to talk about with HSBC. He was
talking about the egregious behavior of
insurance companies that include heavy
use of, yes, you guessed it, offshore
repo. Those people out there making
similarities to 2008, yeah, you can see
it.
And that's not all. Officials
themselves, at the Federal Reserve and
elsewhere, they have already shifted
from saying there's nothing to private
credit, to now they say, "Okay, there is
something, but we don't think it's
catastrophic." Again, it's not what they
say, it's what they actually do. But,
let's start at the beginning, or at
least the beginning of what is now the
latest chapter as the pick your analogy,
the the we peel back the layers of the
private credit onion at the same time as
pulling back the curtain on all of it.
So, yesterday, HSBC reported earnings
that shocked Wall Street and sent the
stock price down by 6%. Now, on the
surface, didn't seem to be too much that
was out of line, but it was one item
that caught the market's attention.
Quote, "The London-based dual-listed
lender booked a total of 1.3 billion in
credit losses, largely driven by a 400
million charge linked to a fraud-related
secondary securitization exposure with a
financial sponsor in the UK." Now,
there's more to this. There's this other
little tidbit, which you'll immediately
recognize as the same problem that keeps
coming up over and over and over again
when it comes to private credit. They
all keep saying their underwriting is
unimpeachable, and the credits that they
own are stunningly solid. Well, does
anyone anywhere ever bother to check for
sure before they write the checks for
hundreds of millions, if not billions of
dollars, or billions of other currency?
Quote, "On Tuesday, Pam Kaur, who's
HSBC's chief financial officer, said the
bank had relied on the financial
sponsor's due diligence, referring to
Apollo, which we'll get to in a second,
when making the loans that led to the
$400 million charge. The bank is working
on additional procedures to vet
borrowers," she added. A little late,
don't you think? The fact that they have
to say they're starting to do now what
they should have been doing from the
very beginning is the reason why HSBC
stock was down 6%. Now, yeah, shares
have recovered since then, but they're
that's just because they're caught up in
the current market euphoria. But, that
initial sell-off speaks to just how much
we all expect the worst at this point
because they keep giving us every reason
to think that way. Now, we know what
that secondary exposure was. That's how
the loss was characterized. It was the
UK cockroach MFS. And in the grand
scheme of things, $400 million is next
to nothing for a bank of the size of
HSBC. But as we've seen from the very
beginning, all the way back with
Tricolor and First Brands, it's not the
amount of money, not yet anyway, it's
more confirmation of widespread bubble
behavior and and quite frankly, way too
much stupidity with next to zero due
diligence. That's the theme we have to
keep coming back to. She said they were
depending upon somebody else to do the
due diligence. That's just crap. That's
garbage. But in prying back the curtain
on private credit and shadow banking,
we're also seeing more of how that
sausage has been made, we're using
another analogy here, and it is not
pretty. And the reason it isn't pretty
is because we've seen this kind of
sausage before. This is where the 2008
comparisons really start to come into
play.
What is a Eurodollar University
membership? It's where understanding the
monetary world isn't a mystery, it's a
method. If you're serious about your
financial education and you want clarity
in a world of volatility and
misunderstanding,
this is for you.
Mainstream education has left so many
gaps on the most foundational concepts,
making sense of everything is
practically impossible otherwise. With
our memberships, we'll fill in
everything that you've been missing.
Whether you're starting out or
sharpening your edge, our memberships
scale with your goals. At Eurodollar
University, we teach you about how money
really works so that you can evaluate
fundamentals and make grounded
decisions. With a Eurodollar University
membership, you get a comprehensive
library of foundational and advanced
lectures, in-depth case studies, and
real-world analyses, live Q&A sessions,
regular updates on macro trends, and
even some central bank policies. And
most important, how to interpret
critical derivative market signals you
will not find anywhere else.
You can't be in position to succeed if
you don't know how it all really works
and fits together. So, if you're ready
to explore master monetary systems both
past and future with structure, clarity,
and confidence,
click the link in the description to
visit eurodollar.university/memberships
to join us today.
So, get a load of this. Going a little
bit further with HSBC here. This is the
part that will be familiar to 2008. Not
talking about subprime mortgages, but
the processes, the general framework,
the behavior, the stench of the
behavior. Quote, HSBC lent to an
Ireland-registered entity of Apollo's
Atlas unit called AEGFWHCO185
Designated Activity
UK and Irish corporate filings. Now,
that Irish entity lent around $650
million to a UK company Zircon Bridging.
Zircon Bridging had a servicing and
origination agreement with Our Cockroach
MFS, which had funded around 525
property loans through Zircon when Atlas
pushed Zircon Bridging into bankruptcy
proceedings in February. Zircon Bridging
wasn't owned by MFS, but by another
company called Zircon Group, controlled
by MFS owner Parish Raja. A spokesperson
for Raja declined to comment. In these
quote back leverage deals, that's a term
that we've talked about before and we'll
get into a little bit more here, the
special purpose vehicles do the
borrowing and the banks have no recourse
on the non-bank lender, which really
puts the onus on due diligence, don't
you think? In this case, Apollo's Atlas
unit, if the underlying assets do sour
because an MFS unit allegedly double
pledged its collateral, there may be
little for HSBC and the other lenders to
recover in the a huge mess. Now, some of
this is missing the point. As if the
only concern is about the state of
regulated banking. Now, we should be
concerned just as much about the state
of shadow banking given how important it
has become to the flow of money and
credit, especially at the margins, even
if that flow is hidden in the shadows.
So, yes, this can be and can continue to
be an issue for the banks, but being a
major issue for shadow banks already
makes it a possible big problem for
financial markets and the wider economy.
As I talked about in a video last month,
we aren't on the lookout for the next
Lehman. You have to think much broader
than that. Again, even if the money
involved isn't huge, at least in this
one instance, $400 million for the bank
decides of HSBC,
that's not really the point at this
stage. What is the point or several
points at this stage is how all of this
is shaped up, how all of this has been
put together in hidden ways that we see
that are entirely too familiar to 2008.
Plus, confirming yet again the bubble
framework and also the bubble behavior
that goes along with it. Lack of due
diligence, focus on the deals, don't
care about anything other than
tomorrow's big bonus check that comes in
once the deal gets done.
The lack of care and due diligence
really does seem to be endemic, and if
it is, then we're talking about real
money. Especially since it wouldn't be
just HSBC or Barclays or Santander or
the other names that have come up with
this MFS business. As we've talked about
before, ground zero is going to be the
insurance industry. Insurers have been
some of the biggest reachers for yield
across the entire financial spectrum.
Huge buyers of private credit, and as it
turns out, huge fans of using leverage
to really juice their returns, and even
bigger fans of not telling anybody about
that. But not just huge leverage, no,
that's not enough. Huge leverage via
offshore entities that are set up to
both maximize its financial efficiency
as well as obscure the entire thing.
Now, I touched on this part of the
insurance story along with back
leverage, that term we just went over,
in a previous video from a little less
than a month ago. Now, before I get to
the comments from Apollo CEO, let's do
the background on what he's going to be
talking about and the connection between
insurers and offshore repo leverage. So,
let's go back to that previous video
real quick.
Because it's never good enough just to
get a higher coupon from a high-yield
bond. Why not go into repo? Borrow at a
smaller rate and use the funds to
finance much of the bond's purchase. In
that case, you get the higher yield from
the asset itself, but the repo leverage
amplifies those returns into something
extra special. And if you think these
things are risk-free or close to
risk-free, their investment-grade
rating, all the better. And it's much
easier to do when, as a life insurance
company, you've got access to tons of
high-quality collateral like US
Treasuries that are just sitting around
in regulated reserve portfolios. So,
yes, this should sound familiar to
anyone who paid attention in 2007
heading into 2008. Look at what the
diagram shows on the right side for
funding these risky assets. There are
the policyholders, those who own
annuities and and the like, making their
premium payments and putting in upfront
capital. But look just below that,
institutional investors they call them,
like the Federal Home Loan Banks. But
just below that, also repo securities
lending. The insurance company pledges
collateral and borrows short-term
funding in repo markets to gain the
leverage on already risky assets. And
those assets are what are shown on the
left side of the diagram. The private
credit providers like Blue Owl or other
CLO vehicles, leveraged loan
syndications, they take the money they
get from the insurers, which is money
the insurance got from policy holders
plus repo, and then they re-lend it to
the riskier firms, the middle-market
corporate segment. But here's the thing,
because a lot of that repo leverage is
offshore, which is a whole other topic
here, it's largely hidden. Plus, the
structure obscures everything on top of
everything else. From the outside,
everything looks good, solid, steady,
limited leverage. So, it looks like
there's just two to one leverage for the
asset manager, but in reality, it could
be 12 to one, but who the hell really
knows? Now, I'd wager, just like 2008,
none of those who are doing it know
either. The companies themselves, the
repo funders, nobody really knows the
extent of all this. They just do it
because the money looks so darn good.
So, with all that in mind, there are a
couple of key points raised by Apollo
CEO Marc Rowan, starting with the fact
that Apollo's insurance companies are
pulling back from risky credit. They all
say everything's fine, nothing to see
here, but it's not what they say, it
starts with what they're doing. Quote,
"While Apollo is experiencing robust
results today," Rowan said, "he is
preparing for choppier times ahead. The
firm has moved up the credit quality of
its fixed income investments, cut
exposure to riskier sectors like
software, and stockpiled stockpiled
about 40 billion of cash in its
insurance business. It means we're
investing with an eye toward protecting
our capital and making sure that we are
here to ride through the cycles if there
are corrections, which we quite frankly
expect." Again, that's big news because
it shows an awareness of the risk and
confirming those risks are sizable.
Otherwise, Rowan wouldn't have to
wouldn't have his financial firms moving
up the credit quality of its fixed
income and stockpiling an enormous
amount of cash. They keep saying there's
nothing to see here, but it's not what
they say, it's what they do. They tell
you it's no big deal, but then they
tighten down the screws in their own
credit portfolios. But then, this is
another key part. Rowan took it a step
further and called out the rest of the
insurance business, basically accusing
them of all the bad things that we've
been hearing and talking about. Back to
Rowan here. Not everyone in our industry
is doing what they should do. Not
everyone runs their business the way we
have run our business. We do worry about
contagion.
Now, contagion would mean that stress
spreads through the industry, raising
the risk that regulators or central
banks cares about central banks have to
intervene to protect insurance and
retirement customers. That's your
annuities and retirement funds. Now,
Rowan did not name specific firms that
he thought were acting badly, but he
suggested that some insurers are relying
on what he called egregious practices,
including, here we go, offshore Cayman
structures, complex collateralized
loans, and aggressive credit assumptions
that can make some balance sheets look
stronger than they are. So, this is
where the comparisons to 2008 really
apply. It's not the systemic takedown of
the regulated banking system or even big
chunks of it. We're talking about shadow
money moving among shadow banks,
obscuring the line between investors,
lenders, leverage, and leaving no one to
have any idea how it's all really pieced
together. What you end up with is a
complex tangled web of interlocking
relationships, and guess what? In that
situation, the risk of contagion is not
nothing. Now, remember, what's really
behind all this, how we got to stage two
in the credit crisis in the first place,
is the lack of forthright information,
asymmetry. And the more that gets
uncovered and documented, the more
layers of the onion we peel back, the
more curtains we pull open, the worse it
gets. The more we know, the more we wish
we didn't know, especially since it
doesn't line up with public statements,
widely dispersed public statements. In
fact, that's the one of the biggest
problems. They say one thing and what we
find out
isn't what they said. Now, all the
insurance companies kept saying, "No,
there's no leverage here. There's
nothing. Nothing to worry about." And
while they were technically not lying
about it, the technicalities are
functionally irrelevant. There is
leverage, as we went over in the
previous video, and it is tied up with
insurance portfolios, just not directly
as we can see with this HSBC
example. why I wanted to bring it up
here because it really does expose a lot
about how all of this is put together
and how all of it works. Plus, it also
starts to explain how we could have
gotten to this situation where HSBC
is just lending out $400 million on the
say-so of who knows what. Because that's
the other thing here, too. In this
framework, in this structure, the back
leverage, the bank lends to a company
which lends to another company which
lends to another company, the bank
really has no idea who the borrower is
on the final end of it. In fact, they
did not care, which again, bubble
behavior exposed. They didn't care who
the ultimate borrower was because they
thought, "Well, first of all, there's
some collateral in there somewhere, and
second of all, we're getting huge
returns with seemingly no risk, so why
would we want to rock the boat?" And
this is all starting to make officials
uncomfortable, not just in the US, but
over in the UK where they're quasi
stress-testing the banking relationships
of private credit. I mean, this is
something that central bankers would
They would rather talk about anything
else other than something like a credit
card. They would rather talk about flat
beverage and job losses than the
possibility of a credit cycle. That's
how you know this thing is is
progressing. When they go from, "Hey,
this is all big nothing" to "Okay, it's
something," it really is something. I
mean, Jay Powell last month, he gave us
our subprime is contained for this
generation because he also had to admit
there was This was no longer nothing. In
fact, as far as it now stands in the
official world, we have gone from this
is nothing to okay, there is something,
but now they say it's not something
huge. And the latest to say just that is
Michael Barr. Quote, the Federal Reserve
governor said stress in private credit
could spark psychological contagion
leading to a broader credit crunch once
again warning against loosening the
reins on Wall Street at a time of rising
risk. In an interview with Bloomberg
News, Barr said that while direct links
between banks and private credit do not
yet appear super worrisome, is that an
official technical term? There were
other areas of concern such as insurance
sector insurance sectors overlaps with
private lenders and of course the
leverage and hidden leverage that goes
along with it. Then you also have the
problem of kind of psychological
contagion, he said. People might look at
private credit instead of saying this is
an idiosyncratic problem, these were
high-risk loans and the rest of the
corporate sector is different, they
might say, "Wow, there seem to be cracks
in our corporate sector maybe over here
in the corporate bond market, there are
also cracks." Then you could have a
credit pullback that could lead to more
financial strain. And yes, that's
exactly what we went over in our webinar
because that's exactly how this happens.
But see, we went from nothing to see
here to now I see a possible pathway to
contagion and big problems even if Barr
like Powell still downplays the chances.
So from zero to okay, maybe there is a
chance. And we still haven't even
scratched the surface behind insurance
companies and offshore leverage whether
in the back door or out the front.
So what have we been saying about
private credit from the very beginning?
Bubble behavior, garbage lending,
stupidity, all of that stuff. Do the
deals, volume, lack of due diligence. It
continues to pop up. Not only does it
continue to pop up as we peel back the
onion and we peel back the curtains and
whatever the we look at the sausage
being made, what does it show? Exactly
that and only that.
They all just signed contracts without
checking what they were signing or even
figure out who was on the other end
actually borrowing the money. That is
exactly what HSBC's loss shows us and
you better believe this is not the only
way or the only example. This is how
these things are structured. When they
talk about back leverage, think about
that Irish company with a name like a
Star Wars droid. That's not the only
one. They didn't care who was borrowing
because the returns were just way too
good to pass up. Do the deal, do the
deal, do the deal. But in order to get
those deals done, they had to engineers
all kinds of hidden arrangements
piggybacking on the good names of
regulated insurance companies to take on
big-time leverage via couple of ways,
but in large part offshore repo. That's
fine when everything's going well and
collateral is being valued at top
prices. If or maybe when it doesn't go
well and collateral starts to be
questioned as it has been more recently,
then this internationally tangled web
doesn't just unravel a couple of its
threads, one layer of the onion, one
more layer of the onion, one more
curtain pulled back. It can and does
spread to other parts, particularly in
the absence of information, solid
information. The only solid information
that we're getting or that we ever get
is when something goes wrong and various
parties are forced to disclose what they
otherwise never wanted you to know.
So yes, this is not nothing. Now what we
don't know yet is how big of a something
it ends up being. There are going to be
losses. This is going to get messy, but
what we don't know is who's going to get
stuck with the losses and how messy it
will get along the way, but
stick around because we are going to
find out.
If you want to see my full video on
insurance companies and back leverage
and you know, offshore repo and given
what the Apollo CEO just said, it's well
worth your time. The video link below.
As always, thank you very much for
joining me. Huge thank you to all of you
University members and subscribers, and
until next time.
Take care.